Episode Fifteen
Afterimage
早季 あれ
Saki, look!
Someone destroyed the igloo and leveled the snow.
かまくらを壊して
雪をならしたんだ
バケネズミにしては できすぎてる
あの量の雪だろ
The queerat couldn’t have done that.
There was a lot of snow.
真理亜か守が やったんだな
Either Maria or Mamoru did it.
Where did they go?
どっちに行ったのかな？
I don’t know.
分かんない
They made it difficult to track them.
跡を追われないようにしてるな
いちいち
跡を消しながら行ったの？
You think they went through the
trouble of erasing all their tracks?
バケネズミは そうだろうな
That’s probably what the queerat did.
真理亜は守を抱えても
結構 飛べるからな
Maria can fly quite well even if she’s carrying Mamoru.
もう 十分 来たと思う
I think we’ve come far enough.
上がる？
Want to continue on land?
早季！ 大丈夫か？
Saki? Are you okay?
I’m fi—
だい… じょう… ぶ！
Maria…
真理亜… 守…
どこに行っちゃったの？
Mamoru…
Where did you go?
Want to eat lunch?
昼飯にしようか
落ち着いた？
Calmed down?
Thank you.
ありがとう
Why are you thanking me?
何だよ？
I was just thinking you’re really nice.
優しいなって思って…
ねえ
うん？
Hey…
真理亜たち 見つかるかな？
Do you think we can find them?
We will find them.
見つけるんだ
それしか
２人を助ける方法はないだろ？
That’s our only chance of saving them, right?
そのために
こんなところまで来たんだろ？
That’s why we’ve come here.
Yeah.
うん そうだね
You’re right.
あっ！
どうした？
What’s wrong?
Don’t turn around.
振り返らないで…
It’s about a hundred meters behind you.
後ろ 100ｍくらい向こうにいる
What is it?
何が？
たぶん バケネズミ
A queerat, I think.
いた！
I see it.
Can we catch it?
捕まえられる？
It’s too far away.
この距離じゃ無理
もうちょっと近くないと…
We’d have to get closer.
ちっ！ 気づかれた！
It noticed us!
追いかけなきゃ！
We have to chase it!
どこのコロニーかな？
Which colony is it from?
Who knows?
さあ
でも スクォンクではないだろうな
But it isn’t Squonk, is it?
あった こっちね
There’s tracks.
It went this way.
はっ 待て！
Wait!
What happened to me?
あたし どうしたの？
雪庇を踏み抜いたんだ
You fell through the cornice.
Did I fall all the way to the bottom?
下まで落ちたの？
No, I caught you in time.
いや ぎりぎりで止めた
だから
どこもケガはしてないはずだよ
You shouldn’t be hurt.
目を覚まさないから
心配したけど…
I was worried because you wouldn’t wake up, though.
ここは？
Where are we?
驚くなよ
俺たちの探していたとこだ
Don’t be surprised.
It’s the place we’ve been looking for.
まさか… ウソでしょう？
No way…
Seriously?
その まさかだよ
Yeah, seriously.
It’s quite a humble abode, but this is the guest house of the Robber Fly colony.
こんな小屋だけど
塩屋虻コロニーの貴賓室だよ
お目覚めになられたようですね
I see you have regained your senses.
スクイーラ！
Squealer!
お久しぶりでございます 神様
It has been long, gods.
本当ね
スクイーラは元気にしてたの？
It really has.
Have you been doing well in the meantime?
Yes. Lately the chances to show
devotion to my gods have been plentiful.
はい 最近は神様に
ご奉仕させていただく機会も
多くなりまして
I was honored to be bestowed with a most noble name.
ありがたいことに
大変 名誉ある名前まで賜りました
What is it?
どんな名前？
はい！ 野狐丸と申します！
I am now Yakomaru.
我が塩屋虻コロニーも
The Robber Fly colony, too, has made great strides towards recovery.
目覚ましいばかりの
復興 進歩を遂げました
今では近隣のコロニーとの
合併によって
Including the neighboring colonies that we merged with, our numbers now reach eighteen thousand.
総員 18,000員を
数えるまでになりました
This, too, would have been inconceivable if not for the favor of the gods.
これも ひとえに
ご神助の賜物であると…
I’d love to hear about your colony later,
コロニーの話も
また ゆっくり聞きたいけど
今は ちょっと非常事態なんだ
but we kind of have an emergency right now.
君の力を借りたい
We need your assistance.
Most certainly.
かしこまりました
どうか全てを
この野狐丸にお任せください
Please leave it all to your servant Yakomaru.
大恩ある お２人のためとあらば
I would always lay down my life to aid the two that I am so indebted to.
いつでも
この 一命を投げ出す所存です
木蠹蛾コロニーは どこにあるの？
Where’s the Goat Moth colony?
ここから
４ｋｍ～５ｋｍほど北西です
Four or five kilometers to the northwest.
大雀蜂コロニーの傘下にも入らず
It is one of the few remaining independent colonies affiliated with neither the Giant Hornet colony nor our coalition.
私どもの合併にも消極的な
今では数少ない
独立系のコロニーですね
木蠹蛾が どうかいたしましたか？
What would your business with the Goat Moths be?
友達を捜しているんだ
We’re looking for our friends.
I understand.
分かりました
まずは
そのスクォンクという個体を
The fastest way should be to locate the individual called Squonk.
見つけるのが早道のようですね
明日 一番に木蠹蛾コロニーに
向かいましょう
Let us venture to the Goat Moths once the sun rises.
今すぐ行けないの？
We can’t go now?
I understand your feelings in the matter,
but the snowy paths are dangerous at night.
お気持ちは お察しします
夜の雪道は大変危険です
それに木蠹蛾のほうでも
I fear the Goat Moths might also construe our approach as a raid.
襲撃かと勘違いする恐れが
ございますので…
Now then, your food will be here shortly. Please enjoy.
それでは
食事をご用意いたしますので
お召し上がりください
Before we do that,
その前に 女王様に
ご挨拶しておこうと思うんだけど
we would like to greet the queen.
突然 押しかけた
おわびもしたいしな
We’d like to apologize for coming uninvited, too.
そうですか… 承知いたしました
I see.
Very well.
All buildings are connected by underground tunnels.
建物は全て地下のトンネルで
つながっております
こちら側のは
さまざまな物を造る工場です
Here we see factories for a variety of things.
そして ここで生産された
And here stands the first of our buildings made with concrete.
コンクリートで出来た
第１号がこれです
This…
これは？
The assembly hall of the colony.
コロニーの評議場です
コロニーの真ん中は竜穴が
あったんじゃなかったっけ？
Wasn’t the old colony centered around the queen’s nest?
The sixty representatives of us eighteen thousand discuss and decide matters in this building.
コロニーの成員18,000員を
代表する60の評議員が
この中で議論を尽くし
意思決定を行うのです
女王は どこへ行ったの？
Where did the queen go?
コロニー同士の合併により
複数の女王を抱えることになり
As the constituent colonies each brought their own queen,
管理上 １つの建物に集約する
必要もございましたので…
it became necessary to consolidate them under one roof.
じゃあ そこに行きましょう
Then let’s go.
明日のことも
頼んでおかないといけないし
We have to ask her about tomorrow too.
さようでございますか
ただ コロニーの決定は
As you will.
But colony matters are decided by the assembly.
評議会が担っておりますし
明朝の件につきましては
In our particular case, as a representative of the assembly, I will take matters—
評議会を代表しまして
この野狐丸が責任を…
Whatever!
いいんだよ！ ただ ちょっと
挨拶したいだけだから！
We just want to say hello.
Very well.
かしこまりました
何 これ…
What is this?
Please do enter.
どうぞ お入りください
Please follow me.
どうぞ こちらへ
Here lives our queen.
ここにいるのが 私どもの女王です
お久しぶりです
It’s been a long time.
以前に お目にかかった
渡辺早季です
I’m Watanabe Saki. We’ve met.
よく眠っているわ
It’s sleeping.
寝ぼけて
かまれるかもしれないぞ
It might try to bite us in its sleep.
We’d know if she started to wake up.
起きそうになったら分かるから
どうした？
What is it?
ここを照らして！
Bring the light over here!
What are you doing? Come on!
何やってんの 早く！
これ どういうことなんだ？
What the hell is this?
しかたがなかったのです
We had no choice.
You had no choice?
しかたないって…
女王に何をしたの！
What did you do to the queen?
お話しします
どうか外へ参りましょう
I will explain.
Let us go outside.
It was not our intent that the queen end up in such a pitiful state.
私どもとて あのように
過酷な処置を
取りたいとは思いませんでした
女王は私どもコロニー全員の
母なのですから…
She is, after all, the mother of the colony.
Then why?
だったら どうして？
以前 ご覧になったとき
お感じになりませんでしたか？
Did you not feel it when you last saw her?
女王が精神の均衡を
失いつつあったことを…
The queen had not been mentally stable for a while.
ああ なんとなくは…
Yes… We felt that.
どのコロニーでも
女王は絶対の存在でした
Queens used to hold absolute power in all colonies.
私どもの女王も 元々
圧政的な部分はございましたが
Although our queen had always been rather tyrannical,
あれから暴虐の度は
ますます ひどくなり
her atrocities only worsened, until eventually she was consumed by maddened distrust
あげくには妄想的な
さいぎ心に駆られて
復興に尽力していた重臣を
and had all the ministers that were advancing our recovery executed.
次々に処刑してしまったのです
このままでは
我が塩屋虻コロニーは
We were sure our extinction would be only a matter of time.
滅亡するしかないと思いました
だからって…
That’s why you—
We swear absolute loyalty to the colony and queen.
私どもは 全員
コロニーと女王に対して
絶対の忠誠を誓っております
However,
しかし 私どもとて
we are not tools to be discarded.
使い捨てにされる道具では
ございません
神様を除けば この惑星上で
最も高い智能を持った存在です
We are second in intelligence only to the gods on this planet.
そう信じ コロニーの将来を憂える
心ある者どもが
And so, all who worried for the enduring existence of our colony gathered of their own volition, and formed a union.
自然に集まり
｢組合｣を結成いたしました
｢組合？｣
A union?
Yes.
はい 最低限の権利を守るためには
It was necessary to negotiate with the queen to preserve our most basic of rights.
女王と交渉する
必要があったからです
しかし 女王は激怒いたしました
Sadly, the queen was consumed by rage.
She regarded our move as an act of treason!
私どもの動きを
反逆と捉えたのです
そのため やむなく
こういう結果になりました
With great reluctance we chose this path.
こういう結果って…
“This path”?
What’s the point in keeping her alive in this state?
こんなふうにして
生かしている意味あるのかよ！
We did not wish to completely destroy her mental faculties.
決して感情を破壊することを
意図してはおりません
Thereafter, her aggressiveness declined greatly and she became submissive.
その後 攻撃性は なりをひそめ
従順になりました
出産を続け コロニーの拡大に
積極的に貢献してきましたし
She continues to bear children and actively contributes to the growth of the colony.
何より女王自身
穏やかに暮らすことができ
If anything, she can now live more peacefully than ever.
I sincerely believe she is happier now.
幸せであったと私は信じています
しかし なにぶんにも
初めて行われた手術であったため
However, since we had never performed the procedure before, there were several hygienic complications.
衛生面に
若干の問題があったようで
しばしの後に脳炎を発症したため
あのように…
Shortly thereafter, she began suffering from
encephalitis and has been as you saw ever since.
ひどい…
That’s terrible.
Should not all intelligent individuals be given equal rights?
およそ 知性を持った存在には
等しく権利が与えられるべきでは
ないのでしょうか？
私は それを
神様の本から学びました
That is what I read in the books of the gods.
民主主義の大原則です
It is the core principle of democracy.
でも 他の女王は どうなんだよ？
Then what about the other queens?
こんなとこに
放り込む必要があったのか？
Was it necessary to throw them all into the same building?
All colonies were dealing with the same problem to one degree or another.
みな多かれ少なかれ
同じような問題を抱えていました
生殖能力を持つのは
女王だけですから
Only the queen can reproduce,
so her existence is indispensable.
｢女王無し｣では滅びてしまいます
Even so,
しかし だからといって
コロニーが
she should not be able to claim the entire
colony as her possession on those grounds.
女王の占有物だということには
ならないはずです
出産は女王が
政治や軍事などの頭脳労働は
The queen is responsible for childbirth,
whereas intellectual pursuits such as governance and military
leadership are handed to those with the greatest aptitude.
それぞれ 最も
適性のある者が行うというのが
That is the foundation of the Robber Fly colony.
我が塩屋虻コロニーの
基本方針なのです
気に入らないな
どうも気に入らない
I don’t like this.
I really don’t like this.
どうしたの？
Why?
何だか うさんくさいんだよ
This is just really fishy.
言ってってることと腹ん中は
全然 違うって感じで信用できない
What they say and what they think seem completely different.
I can’t trust them.
でも 真理亜たちを見つけるには
協力してもらわないと…
But we need their help if we want to find Maria and Mamoru.
You saw what they did to the queen.
あいつが女王にやったことを
見ただろ？
自分を産んでくれた母親だぜ
She’s their own mother!
How can they do that?
どうして あんなことできるんだ？
それは…
私だって ショックだったわよ
Well…
I mean, it shocked me too.
でも バケネズミは 所詮 獣なのよ
But in the end, they are beasts.
They don’t feel like we humans do.
感情も人間とは違うんだわ
彼らも
自分たちが生き延びるために
They only did that in order to survive.
しかたなく ああしたのよ
Look at you defending them.
ずいぶん
バケネズミの肩を持つんだな
あっ… そうじゃない
That’s not what I…
けど 人間って
Well…
Don’t humans see their own values as universal?
動物に対して
勝手に思いを重ねちゃうでしょ
Like expecting the parents to
sacrifice themselves for the child?
親は子のために
命を投げ出すはずだとか…
でも 現実は
全然 違ったりするじゃない
But is that really realistic?
バケネズミに
人間の倫理観を当てはめるのは
Isn’t it a mistake to judge queerats through the lens of human ethics?
間違いじゃない？
What I meant when I said I don’t like this is… well…
俺が言ってる
嫌な感じっていうのは
なんていうか…
あいつらって むしろ
It’s more like they seem too similar to humans.
人間に似すぎてるって
気がするんだ
確かに あんな動物
他にいないけど…
It’s true that there are no other animals like them.
I have the strange feeling that
they’re trying to replace humans.
あいつら ひょっとしたら
人間に取って代わろうと
してるんじゃないかって気がする
We have no concrete buildings back home.
コンクリートの建物なんか
町にもないぞ
人間が捨てた物質文明を
It can only mean they’re trying to take for themselves the material culture which we abandoned.
自分のものにしようと
してるとしか思えないよ
Where did they learn about it?
あんな知識 どっから来てるんだ？
He said he read about it,
本だって言ってたけど
そんな都合よく
but there’s no way he’d simply come across a book that explained all he wanted to know about.
知りたいことが書かれた本
発掘できるわけないよ
じゃあ 何よ？
So how did he learn about it?
これは想像だけど
This is just my guess, but maybe
Squealer caught a false minoshiro.
スクイーラはミノシロモドキを
捕まえたのかもしれない
でも まさか
バケネズミが人間に逆らって
But isn’t it a little far-fetched that they would oppose humanity and try to replace it?
取って代わろうなんて…
でも やっぱ 無理だな
I guess it’s kind of impossible.
だって 俺たち２人だけだって
I mean, just the two of us could crush this colony.
こんなコロニー
簡単に潰せるもんな
ねえ スクイーラが
女王にしたみたいなこと
Hey, what if Squealer did to a human what he did to the queen?
人間にしたら…
うん？ 何？
What do you mean?
Nah.
何にも…
Never mind.
どうした？
What’s wrong?
早季？
Saki?
Wow.
すげえ…
This is the stronghold of the Goat Moth colony.
ここが木蠹蛾コロニーの要塞です
はあ？
どこに要塞なんかあるんだよ？
What?
I don’t see a stronghold anywhere!
あそこです
あの陰に洞窟が開いております
There!
A cave extends past that shadow.
長い年月をかけて
岩の中に縦横無尽に通路を掘って
They have dug far and deep into the cliff over the years,
いわば 岩全体を
要塞に変えてしまったのです
turning the entire cliff into their stronghold.
アヴァ～
うわっ！
アヴァ～ グヴァ～
どうやら こちらの本気を
見せてやらねば ならないようです
Well, it appears we will have to
demonstrate we are here in earnest!
えっ？
うわっ ちょっ… 待てよ！
Wh— Wait!
戦いに来たわけじゃないのよ！
We didn’t come here to fight!
ですが ご覧のとおり
However, as you can plainly see, they are ignoring our summons.
相手は呼びかけを
完全に無視しております
I will not permit such rudeness!
多少の荒っぽい手段も
やむを得ません！
You have my heartfelt thanks!
誠に ありがとうございます！
我が兵の命を救っていただき
感謝に堪えません！
I am overwhelmed by gratitude,
for you saved the lives of my soldiers!
神様！ 木蠹蛾は
Gods!
The Goat Moths have fired an arrow knowing you are among us!
神様がいらっしゃると知りながら
矢を射かけました！
これは断じて
許すべからず行為です！
Their actions are completely unforgivable!
どうか神罰を！
Bring down divine punishment!
でも １本だけだったし
But isn’t a single arrow perhaps just a mistake?
間違えて
撃っちゃったんじゃない？
たとえ１本でも
神に弓を引く行為は
Even if it is one single arrow,
the drawing of a bow on a god is
a crime serious enough to bring
annihilation to the entire colony!
コロニーを消滅させられても
しかたがない重罪なのです！
Furthermore, this is necessary to further our cause.
それに
このままでは らちが明きません
木蠹蛾どもが こちらの
事情聴取に応じないかぎり
We have no means of finding your friends unless the Goat Moths agree to let us question them!
友神様を捜す すべは
ございません！
分かった しかたないな
All right. We understand.
あんまり ひどいことはしないで
Don’t be too harsh.
That’s enough!
もう いいわ！
ウワア～
イヤ イヨ
スクイーラ！
Squealer!
何でございましょうか？
What is it?
用があるのはスクォンクなんだ！
The one we have business with is Squonk!
早く呼んでくれるように
言ってくれ！
Tell him to bring him here now!
かしこまりました 直ちに
Very well.
Right away.
スクォンク！
Squonk!
私たちを覚えてる？
Do you remember us?
キキキ… はい 神様
Yes, gods.
Where did Maria and Mamoru go?
真理亜と守は どこへ行ったんだ？
I don’t know, gods.
分かイません 神様
分からない？
You don’t know?
でも 真理亜たちと
一緒にいたんでしょ？
Weren’t you with them?
はい でも あちらの神様たちは
遠くへ行きました
Yes.
But those gods went far away.
遠くって… どこだよ
Far away?
Where?
分かりません
I don’t know.
せめて どっちの方向かくらい
分かるだろ
Don’t you at least know the direction?
I don’t know, gods.
分かイません カヴィ様
But I was given a letter.
でも お手グァミ 預かイました
Nakisou na aoringo kakaeteru mune no oku
泣きそうな青リンゴ  抱えてる胸の奥
In my chest, I carry a green apple that wets my eyes
Korogatte tsuyogatte
転がって  強がって
I fall over yet pretend to be strong
Kyuukutsu na sora niramu
窮屈な空睨む
I glower at the sky and it seems to suffocate me
Unmei ni juujun ni
運命に従順に
Do I look like I'd wait quietly
Jukusu no wo matsu mon ka
熟すのを待つもんか
For destiny to ripen it?
Sen no kaze
千の風
The winds
Agaite sakende
あがいて  叫んで
I struggle and scream
Fuke fuke
吹け吹け
Blow and blow
Watashi wa shabondama
わたしはしゃぼん玉
I'm a soap bubble
Soredemo shinjiteru
それでも信じてる
And still I have faith
Yokisenu arashi ni
予期せぬ  嵐に
In a sudden storm
Joushou shite kakou shite
上昇して  下降して
I rise and fall
Aragau shabondama
あらがうしゃぼん玉
I fight, soap bubble that I am
Soredemo ikiteku
それでも生きてく
And still I live on
Hajikeru shunkan niji hanate
弾ける瞬間  虹、放て
I make a rainbow when I burst
私たちは もはや神栖66町で
生きることはできません
We can no longer live in Kamisu’s 66th district.
もう２度と 元には戻れないのです
There is no turning back.
私たちは死んだと
報告してほしいのです
Please tell them we have died.
To be honest, I would have gone with you.
本当なら
あなたと 一緒に行きたかった
FROM
THE
NEW
WORLD